<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tufte-Jekyll</title>
    <description>A Jekyll theme for content-rich sites</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2024 14:18:41 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2024 14:18:41 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Learning Techniques</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Summary of different learning techniques to boost capacity for learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#active-learning&quot;&gt;Active Learning&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#spaced-repetition&quot;&gt;Spaced Repetition&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#mind-mapping&quot;&gt;Mind Mapping&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#self-testing&quot;&gt;Self-Testing&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#active-recall&quot;&gt;Active Recall&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#note-taking&quot;&gt;Note-taking&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#practice-and-application&quot;&gt;Practice and Application&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#mnemonics&quot;&gt;Mnemonics&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#interleaved-practice&quot;&gt;Interleaved Practice&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#group-study&quot;&gt;Group Study&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#pomodoro&quot;&gt;Pomodoro&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#growth-mindset&quot;&gt;Growth Mindset&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#no-multitasking&quot;&gt;No Multitasking&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#minimizing-distractions&quot;&gt;Minimizing Distractions&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#time-management&quot;&gt;Time Management&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#cheat-sheets&quot;&gt;Cheat Sheets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;active-learning&quot;&gt;Active Learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach involves engaging actively with the material rather than passively consuming it. It often includes activities such as discussions, problem-solving, and practical application of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://teaching.cornell.edu/teaching-resources/active-collaborative-learning/active-learning&quot;&gt;Cornell Teaching: Active Learning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spaced-repetition&quot;&gt;Spaced Repetition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spaced repetition is the act of learning and then reviewing at spaced intervals, preferably with increasing intervals between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1-3-7-14: Review day 1 (right after learning), then 3, then 7 and 14 from when you start.&lt;br /&gt;
Tools: &lt;a href=&quot;https://mochi.cards/&quot;&gt;Mochi cards&lt;/a&gt; - My favorite!, &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.ankiweb.net/&quot;&gt;Anki Flashcards&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Mr-Lined-Index-Studying-Notecards/dp/B0944991DM/&quot;&gt;Paper notecards&lt;/a&gt; - My second favorite, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Dry-Erase-Index-Cards-Reusable/dp/B073K3CY52&quot;&gt;Dry erase note cards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mind-mapping&quot;&gt;Mind Mapping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A visual technique that helps organize information hierarchically using diagrams, with key concepts branching out into related subtopics. It aids in understanding relationships between ideas and enhances memory retention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Better memory and recall, Better creativity, Better connections between concepts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nesslabs.com/mind-mapping&quot;&gt;The science of mind mapping: a visual way to make sense of the world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;self-testing&quot;&gt;Self-Testing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Involves testing oneself on the material to assess understanding and retention. It reinforces learning by identifying areas of weakness that require further review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;active-recall&quot;&gt;Active Recall&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Involves retrieving information from memory without the aid of notes or textbooks. It strengthens memory by actively engaging the brain in recalling information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;note-taking&quot;&gt;Note-taking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Involves summarizing and recording key points from lectures or readings. Effective note-taking helps organize information, aids in comprehension, and provides a useful resource for review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;practice-and-application&quot;&gt;Practice and Application&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Involves applying learned concepts through practical exercises or real-world scenarios. It enhances understanding and reinforces learning by demonstrating how theoretical knowledge can be put into practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mnemonics&quot;&gt;Mnemonics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Techniques or strategies used to improve memory retention by associating information with easier-to-remember cues or patterns. Examples include acronyms, rhymes, and visual imagery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interleaved-practice&quot;&gt;Interleaved Practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternating between different topics or types of problems during study sessions. It enhances learning by promoting varied practice and improving retention compared to massed practice on a single topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;group-study&quot;&gt;Group Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collaborative learning where students work together to review material, discuss concepts, and solve problems. It facilitates peer teaching, diverse perspectives, and social reinforcement of learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pomodoro&quot;&gt;Pomodoro&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A time management method where study or work is divided into intervals (typically 25 minutes) separated by short breaks. It helps maintain focus and productivity by breaking tasks into manageable segments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;growth-mindset&quot;&gt;Growth Mindset&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The belief that abilities and intelligence can be developed through effort, perseverance, and learning. It encourages resilience, learning from failures, and embracing challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;no-multitasking&quot;&gt;No Multitasking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on one task at a time rather than attempting to juggle multiple tasks simultaneously. It enhances concentration, reduces errors, and improves productivity and learning outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;minimizing-distractions&quot;&gt;Minimizing Distractions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Removing or reducing distractions in the study environment to maintain focus and concentration. It includes strategies like turning off notifications, finding a quiet space, or using noise-canceling headphones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-management&quot;&gt;Time Management&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Techniques and strategies for effectively allocating and prioritizing time for study, work, and other activities. It involves setting goals, creating schedules, and minimizing procrastination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cheat-sheets&quot;&gt;Cheat Sheets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concise summaries or reference sheets containing key information or formulas. They serve as quick guides for review and are often used for last-minute preparation before exams or assessments.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/24/Learning-Techniques</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/24/Learning-Techniques</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Advice from Terence Tao</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Advice from brilliant mathematician &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terence_Tao&quot;&gt;Terence Tao&lt;/a&gt; on building a career in mathematics.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/does-one-have-to-be-a-genius-to-do-maths/&quot;&gt;Does one have to be a genius to do maths?&lt;/a&gt;
The answer is an emphatic &lt;strong&gt;NO&lt;/strong&gt;. In order to make good and useful contributions to mathematics, one does need to &lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/work-hard/&quot;&gt;work hard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/learn-and-relearn-your-field/&quot;&gt;learn one’s field well&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/dont-be-afraid-to-learn-things-outside-your-field/&quot;&gt;learn other fields&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/learn-the-power-of-other-mathematicians-tools/&quot;&gt;tools&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/ask-yourself-dumb-questions-and-answer-them/&quot;&gt;ask questions&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/attend-talks-and-conferences-even-those-not-directly-related-to-your-work/&quot;&gt;talk to other mathematicians&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/think-ahead/&quot;&gt;think about the “big picture”&lt;/a&gt;. And yes, a reasonable amount of intelligence, &lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/be-patient/&quot;&gt;patience&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/be-professional-in-your-work/&quot;&gt;maturity&lt;/a&gt; is also required. But one does not need some sort of magic “genius gene”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;work-hard&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/work-hard/&quot;&gt;Work hard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My takeaways&lt;/em&gt;: Work hard. Relying on intelligence alone does not work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From the blog&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;br /&gt;
One needs to do a serious amount of reading and writing, and not just thinking, in order to get anywhere serious in mathematics. Relying on intelligence alone to pull things off at the last minute may work for a while, but, generally speaking, at the graduate level or higher it doesn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learn-and-relearn-your-field&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/learn-and-relearn-your-field/&quot;&gt;Learn and relearn your field&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My take-aways&lt;/em&gt;: How to think critically and question assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From the blog&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;br /&gt;
Just because you know a statement and proof of Fundamental Lemma X, you shouldn’t take that lemma for granted; instead, you should dig deeper until you really understand what the lemma is all about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you find alternate proofs? 
Do you know why each of the hypotheses are necessary?
What kind of generalizations are known/conjectured/heuristic?
When is it a good idea to use the lemma, and when isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ask-yourself-dumb-questions--and-answer-them&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/ask-yourself-dumb-questions-and-answer-them/&quot;&gt;Ask yourself dumb questions – and answer them!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My takeaways&lt;/em&gt;: Avoid passive reading, actively critique the material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From the blog&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;br /&gt;
Don’t just read it; fight it! Ask your own questions, look for your own examples, discover your own proofs. Is the hypothesis necessary? Is the converse true?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;enjoy-your-work&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/enjoy-your-work/&quot;&gt;Enjoy your work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dont-be-afraid-to-learn-things-outside-your-field&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/dont-be-afraid-to-learn-things-outside-your-field/&quot;&gt;Don’t be afraid to learn things outside your field&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My takeaways&lt;/em&gt;: Dont pigeonhole yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From the blog&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;br /&gt;
If it turns out that in order to make progress on your problem, you have to learn some external piece of mathematics, this is a good thing – your own mathematical range will increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;attend-talks-and-conferences-even-those-not-directly-related-to-your-work&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/attend-talks-and-conferences-even-those-not-directly-related-to-your-work/&quot;&gt;Attend talks and conferences, even those not directly related to your work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My takeaways&lt;/em&gt;: Talk to other researchers. Explore what’s going on in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From the blog&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;br /&gt;
You need to know what’s going on elsewhere in mathematics, and what other mathematicians find interesting; this will often give valuable perspectives on your own work. (Yes, it is possible to solve a major problem after working in isolation for years – but only after you first talk to other mathematicians and learn all the techniques, intuition, and other context necessary to crack such problems.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;be-professional-in-your-work&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/be-professional-in-your-work/&quot;&gt;Be professional in your work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My takeaways&lt;/em&gt;: Being professional in workplace and with colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From the blog&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;br /&gt;
Take your duties and responsibilities seriously; being frivolous is fine with friends, but can be annoying for your colleagues, especially those who are busy with similar responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exercise professional courtesy and respect for the time and efforts of your colleagues.  Unless you are already on good casual terms with the person you are interacting with, send them an email (or text, if you are close enough to share phone numbers) to schedule a call or meeting rather than just showing up or calling unannounced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;think-ahead&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/think-ahead/&quot;&gt;Think ahead&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My takeaways&lt;/em&gt;: Try to pause and recall the bigger picture of pursuing a particular goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From the blog&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;br /&gt;
Worse than being blind, is to see and have no vision.
It is really easy to get bogged down in the details of some work and not recall the purpose of what one is actually doing; thus it is good to pause every now and then and recall why one is pursuing a particular goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;be-patient&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/be-patient/&quot;&gt;Be Patient&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My takeaways&lt;/em&gt;: Being patient. Hard problems take large effort. Take advantage of breakthroughs by eliminating &lt;em&gt;fruitless avenues of attack&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From the blog&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;br /&gt;
If I have ever made any valuable discoveries, it has been owing more to patient attention, than to any other talent. - Issac Newton&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any given problem generally requires months of effort in order to make satisfactory progress.  While it is possible for routine or unexpectedly easy problems to fall within weeks, this is the exception rather than the rule. Thus it is not uncommon for months to pass with no visible progress; however by patiently eliminating fruitless avenues of attack, you are setting things up so that when the breakthrough does come, one can conclude the problem in relatively short order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;be-flexible&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/be-flexible/&quot;&gt;Be flexible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My takeaways&lt;/em&gt;: Unpredictable field. Be flexible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From the blog&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;br /&gt;
Mathematical research is by its nature unpredictable – if we knew in advance what the answer would be and how to do it, it wouldn’t be research! You should therefore be prepared for research to lead you in unexpected directions, and it may end up that you may find a new problem or area of mathematics more interesting than the one you were initially working in.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2024 13:04:01 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/24/Terence-Tao-Advice</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/24/Terence-Tao-Advice</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Entelechy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In philosphy or metaphysics, actuality or realisation as opposed to potentiality.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aristotle used the word to refer to the soul (psyche), seen as that form within the material being by virtue of which it achieves the actuality of its nature. In certain vitalist philophies or theories, entelechy refers to the vital force within an organism that allows for life, development and self-fulfillment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aristotle’s idea of entelechy is when potential is fully realized and actualized. A common example is an acorn. An acorn’s state of entelechy is for it to become a tree. For an acorn, its state of entelechy is rather simple and well defined. A person’s state of entelechy has to be defined by that person (or does it?). If something (potential) can be realized and subsequently actualized, this implies that the potential form already exists in abstraction, it simply needs to be identified and given a physical manifestation. Humans have an understanding of the future, which is how we understand potential. Potential is something that can only be acted on through time. So for the acorn, does the tree that it can potentially become exist before it takes on a physical manifestation? It technically does in abstraction, it simply hasn’t been actualized yet. It can be argued that many potential versions of you exist in abstraction at this very moment. As time moves on, potential selves are being “burned off” or “left behind” as you zone in on one. Every person should realize what their state of entelechy is and act through time in such a way so that the self-defined potential self has the highest chance of being actualized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newworldencyclopedia.org/entry/Entelechy&quot;&gt;Newworldencyclopedia&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/philosophy/comments/ss1zhc/aristotles_concept_of_entelechy_when_all/&quot;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 13:04:01 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/24/Entelechy</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/24/Entelechy</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
